<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Judah's restitution A sermon preached before the reverend judges, Sir Christopher Turner Baron of the Exchequer, and Sir Richard Bernard Serjeant at Law. At the assizes begun at Yorke the 29 of July, 1661. By Jos: Hunter Master of Arts and Minister in Yorke.</title>
            <author>Hunter, Josiah, minister in York.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45207</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3767</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203804</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99825286</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99825286</idno>
            <idno type="VID">29664</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45207)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 29664)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2171:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Judah's restitution A sermon preached before the reverend judges, Sir Christopher Turner Baron of the Exchequer, and Sir Richard Bernard Serjeant at Law. At the assizes begun at Yorke the 29 of July, 1661. By Jos: Hunter Master of Arts and Minister in Yorke.</title>
                  <author>Hunter, Josiah, minister in York.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 7-37, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Alice Broade,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Yorke :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Copy filmed has stained title page affecting legibility.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library, Oxford.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:29664:1"/>
            <p>JVDAH'S RESTITUTION. A Sermon preached before the Reverend Judges, Sir <hi>Chriſtopher Turner</hi> Baron of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer, and Sir <hi>Richard Bernard</hi> Serjeant at Law.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>At the Aſsizes begun at Yorke the</hi> 29 <hi>of July,</hi> 1661.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Joſ: Hunter</hi> Maſter of Arts and Miniſter in Yorke.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>
               <hi>YORKE,</hi> Printed by Alice Broade, 1661.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:29664:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:29664:2"/>
            <head>To the right Worſhipfull Sir <hi>THOMAS SLINGSBEY,</hi> High-Sheriffe of the Countie of YORKE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOu was pleaſed to command me out to an Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble but hard Worke, which though ſlenderly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by me) yet hath been kindly accepted by you, and earneſtly deſired by others to be made publique: and <hi>I</hi> am the rather induced to do it, that <hi>I</hi> might give unto the world a teſtimony and acknowledgement of that eſteem and gratitude, which I owe you for your abundant and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſerved Reſpects to me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> confeſſe, you ran a very great hazard, when you made choice of me for ſuch a ſervice: and I might at once both have ſomething leſſened your <hi>Credit,</hi> and quite loſt mine owne; which perhaps was the expectation of ſome, who (though they differed in other things) agreed in this: but whether they were diſappointed of their expectation or no, your <hi>Worſhipp</hi> is able to give the fulleſt account and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer. I have formerly upon the intreaty, and advice of freinds, expoſed a <hi>Sermon</hi> of two unto common cenſure, and if any will be at the pains to compare them with this, they ſhall find no contradiction, which made me the more willing to adventure this.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:29664:3"/>
            <p>And now that it is put out, if it were worth the owning, there is none hath more right to it than your <hi>Selfe.</hi> I deſire no more, and I hope you will grant no leſſe than this, that as this <hi>Sermon</hi> had your <hi>Command</hi> for its <hi>production,</hi> ſo it may have have your <hi>Patronage</hi> for its <hi>preſervation. I</hi> know it is uſuall to fill <hi>Epiſtles Dedicatorie</hi> with the praiſes of the Perſon, unto whom the <hi>Dedication</hi> is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected; but his <hi>Majeſty</hi> hath ſo much honoured you in preferring you to ſuch a place of <hi>Truſt</hi> &amp; <hi>Credit</hi> in your <hi>Country,</hi> and you have ſo farre honoured your <hi>Selfe</hi> in the diſcharge of it, beyond the expectation of your years, that I need ſay nothing. I will rather turne my <hi>Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> into <hi>Counſell,</hi> that you would ſtudie ſo to improve your time, your <hi>Abilities,</hi> and your <hi>experience</hi> (ever having before you for your patterne, the <hi>Sobrietie</hi> and <hi>reſervedneſſe</hi> of your honoured <hi>Father</hi>) that you may ſtill deſerve the <hi>Royall Favour,</hi> be more fit to do God &amp; your <hi>Country</hi> ſervice, and live long (<hi>I</hi> do not ſay to be envied) but if envied, for nothing elſe, but deſerved <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Happineſſe.</hi> So prayes</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>Your Worſhips moſt humble ſervant, Joſiah Hunter.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:29664:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Iſaiah 1</hi> chap: <hi>26</hi> verſe.</bibl>
                  <p>And I will reſtore thy Judges as at the firſt, and thy Counſellours as at the beginning: afterward thou ſhalt be called the Citie of Righteouſneſſe, the faithfull Citie.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Text deſerves your more ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous attention, becauſe taken out of the Prophecy of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> which (for the divine matter thereof,<note place="margin">ſee <hi>Robert's</hi> key of the Bible. v. <hi>Hieron.</hi> ſup. <hi>Jeſch.</hi>
               </note> mixed with ſo many flouriſhes of humane learning) hath ever been of high eſteem in the Church.</p>
            <p>Chriſt (who might be ſaid to preach all Text) yet ſometime in his preaching, tooke a Text out of this Prophet, as you may ſee <hi>Luke</hi> 4.17, 18. and this prophecy is quoted oftner in the new Teſtament, than any other book of the old Teſtament except the pſalmes:<note place="margin">Alſted., <hi>in praecog. Theol.</hi> lib: 2. c. 122</note> whether <hi>Alſtedius</hi> himſelfe was at the paines of the obſervation or no, I know not, but he tells us, that <hi>Iſaiah</hi> is alledged ſixtie times &amp; the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:29664:4"/> Pſalmes but ſixtie four times in the new Teſtament Amongſt the very Ethiopians this Book was in ſuch repute, that the Queens Evnuch made it (his <hi>vade mecum</hi>) his companion in his journey, and read the prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> in his charion, though he underſtood him not, <hi>Act.</hi> 27, 28. and St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſo highly eſteemed &amp; valued this prophecy, that when <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> wrote to him for his advice, what part of Scripture he ſhould eſpecially read, he adviſed him to read the prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> himſelfe tels us. <hi>Lib: confeſ:</hi> 9. ca. 5.</p>
            <p>For the dependence of the words, <hi>Hyperius</hi> his note upon the Text is of good uſe. It is familiar with the Prophets (ſaith he) firſt to declare unto the people their ſins, then to threaten puniſhment, and laſt of all to let fall ſome promiſes of mercy; the firſt to convince them and beget ſorrow; the ſecond, to humble them and work fear; the third, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort them &amp; erect hope. This method our prophet obſerves exactly. For, firſt he diſcovers their ſins to them from the 2. unto the 24. verſe. 2: He denounces judgment againſt them, 24, 25. ver. 3: He ſcatters ſome promiſes of mercy, 26, 27. verſes.</p>
            <p>The ſtate of the Jewes (you may conceive) was very much declining &amp; tending to ruine: the gracious God, who alwayes in judgment remembers mercy, promiſes unto them the proviſion of a remedie,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:29664:4"/> every way ſuitable to their maladie, a reſtiſtution according to their defection, Their defection is noted to be generall, in the whole body of the people, ver. 21. <hi>How is the faithfull City become an harlot, it was full of judgment, righteouſneſſe lodged in it, but now murtherers:</hi> the particular cauſe of this generall defection is noted to be the corruption of their Governours, ver. 23. <hi>Thy Princes are rebellious &amp; companions of theeves, every one loveth gifts &amp; fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth after rewards, they judge not the fatherles, neither doth the cauſe of the widow come unto them.</hi> Now ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, how ſutable the remedie in the Text, is to the maladie in the context. They were declined, God promiſeth, <hi>I will reſtore:</hi> the cauſe of their defection was the infection or corruption of their Rulers; accordingly God promiſeth to remove that, by reſtoring their Judges as at the firſt, and thir Counſelours as at the begining; and now <hi>(ſublatâ cauſa tolletur effectus)</hi> the faithfull Citie ſhall be no more called an Harlot or a Sanctuarie for murtherers, but it ſhall be called, (as it was wont to be,) <hi>the Citie of righteouſneſſe, the faithfull Citie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will a little open the words, and when the ſhell is broken, it is eaſier to take out the meat and dreſſe it. <hi>And I will reſtore thy &amp;c. And</hi>) that is the <hi>Copula,</hi> which joynes the Text and the precedent verſe together, <hi>I will turne mine hand upon thee &amp;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:29664:5"/> purely purge away thy droſſe, and take away all thy tinne, and I will reſtore thy Judges as at the firſt:</hi> you may take notice, how evill Governours are like impure, corrupt and droſſie mettalls, theſe God would purge away: but becauſe this was in it ſelfe but a privative mercie, therefore he adds a poſitive in the Text, <hi>And I will reſtore thy Judges as at the firſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I will reſtore</hi>) there is a double reſtitution; one <hi>ex debito,</hi> another <hi>ex dono.</hi> One due, another free. Due reſtitution is, when having taken away any thing unjuſtly,<note place="margin">non remitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur peccatum, niſi reſti na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur abla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um.</note> we returne it again either in <hi>quali</hi> or in <hi>quanto:</hi> and this reſtitution is very neceſearie, for as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, without this reſtitution to men, we can expect no remiſſion from God, for this reſtitution, <hi>Zacheus</hi> is famous, <hi>Luke</hi> 19.8. Free reſtitution is, when a man hath forfeited his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in a thing, and he, to whom it is forfeited, is willing out of clemencie and bountie, to releaſe the forfeiture &amp; re-enſtate him againe. Such is this reſtitution promiſed in the Text, not a Due, but a Free reſtitution. The Jews had forfeited all their priviledges and immunities, and deſerved ruine rather than reſtauration; yet God promiſed to reſtore them, and now indeed, that he hath promiſed, he is become a debtor to his own word, but he was not bound before.</p>
            <p>I <hi>will reſtore thy Judges,</hi>) Judges may be taken
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:29664:5"/> here, either more largely, or more ſtrictly: more largely, for all ſorts of Magiſtrates. For all Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates are in ſome ſenſe Judges, and frequently ſo termed in Scripture, <hi>(ad denotandam facultatem)</hi> to note their Abilitie, they ſhould be able to judge, or elſe they are not qualified to be Magiſtrates; and <hi>(ad denotandam poteſtatem)</hi> to note their authoritie: they have power by their Office to judge <hi>(inter deum &amp; reum)</hi> between God and the guilty, in matters of ſacriledge &amp; blaſphemie: <hi>(inter Regem &amp; reum)</hi> between the King &amp; the guilty, in matters crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and contrary to the Law of the land: and laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>(inter meum &amp; tuum)</hi> in matters of right &amp; wrong, between partie &amp; partie, when they are in contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie about any Claime or Title. or</p>
            <p n="2">2: Judges may be taken here more ſtrictly, for ſuch as are lawfullie deputed, not only to execute, but alſo to expound &amp; interpret the Law, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that to give ſentence. And that there was ſuch an honourable office, wherewith ſome were eſpecially intruſted among the Jews, is plain enough out of the Scripture. The Arche-type, or firſt draught of the office of Judges under the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Magiſtrate, you have. <hi>Exod.</hi> 18:25. where it is ſaid that <hi>Moſes</hi> (following the advice of <hi>Iethro</hi>) choſe men out of all Iſrael, and they judged the people at all ſeaſons: and now this office being once
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:29664:6"/> invented &amp; erected, and by experience found to be of great advantage; we read frequently afterwards in ſcripture of Judges taken in this ſtrict ſenſe. Particularly, it is ſaid of <hi>Jehoſaphat</hi> 2. <hi>Chro.</hi> 19.5. <hi>He ſet Judges in the land throughout all the fenced Cities of Judah, Citie by Citie.</hi> And the Scripture tels us, how <hi>Samuel</hi> (judge in Iſrael) uſed to ride the Circuit every yeare, 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.15. <hi>Samuel judged Iſrael all the dayes of his life, and he went from year to year in Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuit, to Bethel, and Gilgal, and Mizpeh, and judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Iſrael in all thoſe places, and his return was to Ramah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I will reſtore thy Judges &amp; thy Counſellours</hi>) who are meant by Counſellors in the Text? <hi>Rem eandem bis dicit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">in commen: ſup: cap. 1. <hi>Jeſch.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>namijdem ſunt Conſiliarij, qui Judices:</hi> Thus <hi>Marlorate. Non denotat duos ſeparatos ſtatus, ſed tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum geminum officuim.</hi> ſo <hi>Urſin &amp; muſculus.</hi> All Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitors, that I had by me to conſult with, do run this way, and conclude that Judges and Counſellors are both the ſame perſons; only here is <hi>(duplex no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men)</hi> becauſe there is <hi>(duplex officium)</hi> they have a double Title given them, to note a double dutie required of them, which is not only to give judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>(in rebus litigioſis)</hi> but alſo to give Counſell <hi>(in rebus arduis)</hi> Judges &amp; Counſellours are both one here in the text, though not ſo amongſt us: yet this we may ſafely ſay, though every Counſellour be not a Judge, yet every judge ought to be a Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:29664:6"/> nor is he fit to give judgment, that cannot give Counſell. They do greatly dote, and are deceived (ſaith <hi>Muſculus</hi>) who think that Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth: can be well govern'd by ſimple, good men. As much goodneſſe, and as little guile as you will,<note place="margin">admodum de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſipiunt, qui potant Reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publicas poſſe gubernari per viros ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices &amp; bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos. <hi>in loc: ſupr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit:</hi>
               </note> in Governers; But to the due qualification of a Governour, eſpecially a Judge, it is not ſufficient that he be an honeſt good man, but he muſt alſo be a wiſe &amp; prudent: ſuch were the judges God promiſed unto <hi>Judah,</hi> judges that ſhould be Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours too.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I will reſtore thy judges as at the firſt, &amp; thy Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours as at the beginning,</hi>] there is ſome ſmal difference amongſt Commentators, how farre to extend this, <hi>ab initio &amp; in principio.</hi> Some are of opinion, that it is to be referred as farre as <hi>Moſes, Joſhua</hi> and ſo along to the time of the judges, whilſt, as yet,<note place="margin">Muſeul. <hi>&amp;</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſin in com. ut ſupra.</note> they had no King. God would reſtore them ſuch judges as they were, not only for qualities but alſo for forme: and they that are of this opinion, do hold that God here ſpeaks <hi>(de rejectione regum &amp; reductione judicum)</hi> as though (when he reſtored <hi>Judah</hi>) they ſhould no longer be governed by Kings, but by judges, as they were before they had a King: and ſo indeed it fell out after the Babilonian captivity, and therefore <hi>Lyranus</hi> thinks the judges, the Text ſpeaks of, were <hi>Zerobabel, Nehemiah, Ezra, the Macca bees,</hi> and ſuch like.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:29664:7"/>
            <p>But others there are that ſay <hi>(melius referuntur haec ad tempora Davidis)</hi> this,<note place="margin">Marlorase</note> at the firſt and in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, is better referred to the times of <hi>David,</hi> for in his time <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> firſt became famous, both becauſe it was the Seat of the King, and alſo the Seat of Gods Worſhip: and ſo God promiſeth that he would reſtore unto the Kingdome of judah, Governours and judges that ſhould be like unto <hi>David,</hi> Men after his own heart.</p>
            <p>If I might caſt in mine owne conjecture amongſt ſuch learned men, it ſhould be this. We need not much to trouble our ſelves in enquiring to what times this ſhould have reference, ſeing the ſimple &amp; genuine meaning of the place is this: I <hi>will give unto thee Judges, that ſhall be able &amp; upright, pious &amp; prudent,</hi> that ſhall helpe to reduce the ſtate of Judah unto order &amp; eſtabliſhment, as much as the corrupt judges have brought it neer unto ruine &amp; confuſion: and the reaſon why it is ſaid, <hi>as at the firſt, and in the beginning,</hi> is to note how very good thoſe Judges (which God would reſtore them) ſhould be or every thing it is thought to be beſt in <hi>primordiis,</hi> in its orignall, at firſt, corruptions creep in with time. This therefore, I conceive, may be the ſenſe of the place. I <hi>will reſtore thy judges as at the firſt,</hi> that is, I will reſtore unto thee very good Judges, Judges of the firſt impreſſion, judges according to the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:29664:7"/> before perſonall abuſes had crept into and mingled themſelves with the Office.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Afterward thou ſhalt be called,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Afterward</hi>] not before this reſtitution: things &amp; perſons are to be called, as they are. If Jeruſalem be fallen off and degenerated, though ſhe was called before the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Citie, yet now ſhe deſerves no better name then harlot: if ſhe be return'd &amp; reſtor'd again to her primitive integrity, though ſhe was for a time called Harlot, yet now ſhe ſhall be called again, the Citie of rihgteouſneſſe, the faithfull Citie. We muſt not call darknes light, nor light darknes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou ſhalt be called</hi>] of God, of the King,<note place="margin">Iſa. 5:20.</note> of the people. <hi>The Citie of righteouſnes</hi>] becauſe of the due &amp; impartiall adminiſtration of juſtice in thee. <hi>The faithfull Citie</hi>] Jeruſalem was called the faithfull Citie for two reaſons; firſt with reference to God, becauſe they obſerved and upheld the true worſhip of God, a great deale more than <hi>Samaria</hi> or any Citie of Iſrael did, who worſhipped the Calves that <hi>Jero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam</hi> had ſet up. Secondly, the faithfull Citie with reference to the King, becauſe they kept their Loyalty &amp; Allegiance to the ſucceſſors of David, whom God had ſet up, whereas the Cities of Iſrael revolted from him &amp; rebelled againſt him under <hi>Jeroboam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The text thus explained, I will trouble you with
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:29664:8"/> no other diviſion than this: it is a gracious promiſe; of what? of reſtitution: <hi>I will reſtore.</hi> Of whom? of Judges and Counſellours: I <hi>will reſtore thy judges and thy Counſellours.</hi> In what manner? as at the firſt and as in the beginning. With what ſucceſſe? <hi>after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward thou ſhalt be called, the Citie of Righteouſneſſe, the faithfull Citie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Before I enter upon theſe particulars, I ſhall ſpeak this by way of introduction. Be not offended, if I do as it is likely I ſhall this day deceive many of you, in your expectation of two things; and they are Rhetorique and Reflection. For Rhetorique, I know indeed, that <hi>modus orationis eſt auditor:</hi> and eloquence ſhould fall from this place, like <hi>Sions</hi> ſilver drops, upon the lower ground: but as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid once, ſo do I now, my Lords I am not eloquent, neither have I the tongue of the learned. For reflexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on perhaps ſome expect I ſhould handle the Text ſo; but I am more mindfull of his Majeſties <hi>Act of Oblivion,</hi> which if I ſhould in this place and at this time,<note place="margin">Job 31.28.</note> in the leaſt violate, it would be an iniquitie (as <hi>Iob</hi> ſpeaks in another caſe) an iniquitie to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed by the judges. This being premiſed I begin with the firſt. What it is that is promiſed? it is a reſtitution, I <hi>will reſtore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Reſtitution is of a middle nature, between Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion &amp; preſervation: it is not ſo much as Creation,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:29664:8"/> yet it is more than ordinary preſervation. The ſtate of Iudah was not wholly deſtroyed, therefore there needed not a Creation: yet it was much decayed, therefore there was great need of a Reſtauration.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Reſtitution is not ſo much as Creation. The Iews, though much relapſed, yet were not quite ruined, therefore they needed not a creation: their ſtate was like an houſe, much ruined, yet the the foundation remaining. The Pſalmiſt in one place complains,<note place="margin">Pſal: 82.5.</note> that all the foundations of the earth were out of courſe: ſo it was now with the Jewes, all their foundations were unſetled, yet not quite eradicated. There was ſomething to build on, therefore no neceſſitie of a Creation, or a making all things new.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They had their fundamentall Governement un-interupted; continued under Kings and in the right Line. For <hi>Iſaiah</hi> prophecyed in the dayes of <hi>Uzziah, Iotham, Ahaz</hi> &amp; <hi>Hezekiah</hi> Kings of Judah, chap: 1. verſe 1. All Kings and lawfull Heirs to the Crown. <hi>Uzziah</hi> the lawfull Son and heire to <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ziah: Iotham</hi> Son and heir to <hi>Uzziah: Ahaz</hi> Son and heir to <hi>Iotham;</hi> and <hi>Hezekiah</hi> Son and heir to <hi>Ahaz.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiph.</hi> in vit. prophet.</note> It is thought indeed, that he propheſied alſo in the dayes of <hi>Manaſſeh,</hi> and was by his commandment ſawne aſunder: grant it, yet <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> was ſtill the Son and heir of <hi>Hezekiah.</hi> All this while the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:29664:9"/> was not changed, nor the ſucceſſion inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted. Here might need a reſtitution of ſome ſuch Kings, as <hi>David, Solomon, Iehoſaphat,</hi> but none of the Government, for it was not altered.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They retained their fundamentall Lawes, which God preſcribed them by <hi>Moſes</hi> for their Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernement, as they were a Civill ſtate, that is, thoſe which we call (by way of diſtinction) Iudiciall Lawes. However they did not obſerve them, yet we read not, that they obliterated them, or made any others contrary to them. defects in the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Lawes, and perverting of judgment, is a thing ſo ordinarie, that the wiſe man bids us, we ſhould not wonder at it, 5. <hi>Eccleſ</hi> 8. However therefore they might be corrupt in the execution of their Lawes, yet they did not ſubvert them, but ſtill in profeſſion retained them, and had them in reverence, as their <hi>MAGNA CHARTA,</hi> from the King of heaven.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They ſtill retained the Foundation of their Religion. It cannot be denied, but they borrowed many corrupt mixtures, both from Forreign Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and from their next Neighbours &amp; Brethren the idolatrous Iſraelites, which did very much ſtain the purity, and darken the luſtre of their Religion: but ſtill God owned them for a true Church, and his own Spowſe. Though he gave a bill of divorce to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:29664:9"/> Iſrael, <hi>Ier.</hi> 3:8. yet we read not of any Bill of divorce he gave to Iudah.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Reſtitution is more than ordinary preſervation. It requires more skill and power in the Agent, becauſe it ſuppoſeth more unfitneſs and indiſpoſition in the Patient. It is with bodies po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litique, as it is with Bodies naturall; it is eaſier to preſerve them in health and harmony, than it is to reſtore them, when once a decay or diſorder hath fallen upon them. That the jewiſh State was much decayed, is plain enough. Their Princes and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours very corrupt, ſo farr diſloyall, that they were rebellious, and ſo far degenerate, that they were companions of Theeves. Their Lawes in being, but not in force, notoriouſly violated by the people, and perverted by the judges, inſomuch that our Prophet ſaith, chap 59. v: 14. Iudgment was turned back ward, and juſtice ſtood afar off; Truth was fallen in the ſtreet and equitie could not enter. Their Religion alſo was horiblie defiled, by a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt mixture of idolatrous inventions with it, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in their divine worſhip: not only Iſrael played the Harlot, but Judah alſo, ſo much, as if ſhe would out-ſtrip Iſrael in ſpirituall whoredome, as you may ſee <hi>Jer:</hi> 3.9, 10. Here was very great neceſſitie of a Reſtitution therefore, or elſe this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay would ſoone have brought them to deſtruction.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:29664:10"/>
            <p>But will ſome ſay, it is true, Reſtitution is a greater worke than preſervation: but the Lord, if he ſo pleaſed, might ſave himſelfe this labour, if he would (as we know he can) preſerve a Church or Nation from decaies, then he needed not to be at the paines of a Reſtitution. Why then doth God ſuffer ſuch decaies, conſumptions &amp; over-turnings to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall a people, when he can prevent them?</p>
            <p>There are two reaſons for it, the one is taken from his juſtice, the other is taken from his Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. The firſt is taken from his juſtice: thus it pleaſeth him many times to puniſh the ſins of a wanton, unthankfull, ſecure, proud &amp; contentious people. They firſt break with God, &amp; then God ſends breaches upon them. You muſt conſider, that God will not ordinarily worke miracles for the preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of any Nation, but in his common providence lets every thing work in it's courſe, and according to the diſpoſition of ſecond cauſes. Its no wonder to ſee an unſound body fall into decay, its true God could preſerve it if he would, but he will not worke a miracle in croſſing natures courſe: So uſually States are unſound and diſeaſed, full of diſtempers and corrupt humours, before they fall into decay, God could, if he would, heal all; but he will not ſtep out of the way of his ordinarie providence: things ſhall work as they are diſpoſed. He will not work
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:29664:10"/> a miracle to preſerve a ſinfull people, but is rather reſolved for their many provocations, to ſend upon them a conſunption, and a languiſhment.</p>
            <p>The ſecond reaſon is drawne from Gods wiſdome. He ſuffers theſe decaies to befall a people. Firſt that they may ſee and be ſenſible of their own im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prudence. <hi>Every wiſe woman buildeth her houſe, but the fooliſh plucketh it down with her hands. Prov:</hi> 14. 1. Some ſuch fooliſh people there are too (though they thinke themſelves wiſe) who becauſe they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like ſomething in the building and preſume they can eaſily reare up and reforme all againe, pluck downe a whole Nation. God lets them alone, he knowes they will ſoone be warped in their owne folly; and at laſt they learne that it had been better to have ſuffered ſome things, which they conceived amiſſe, than to have endangered the deſtruction of the <hi>Whole.</hi> How doth the fooliſh woman pluck down her houſe? ſhe either plucks it downe, becauſe ſhe is fickle, and would have her houſe changed too: or elſe becauſe ſhe is fooliſh, and knows not how to governe her houſe: and thus it falls out often, that becauſe Governours are imprudent, and the people deſirous of change, they pluck downe a Nation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them. And the wiſe God ſuffers it, that at laſt they may ſee their own follie.</p>
            <p n="2">2. God in wiſdome ſuffers ſuch decaies, to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:29664:11"/> make people more, thankfull for their reſtitution. It is the epidemicall diſeaſe of Man-kind, to take notice of the price of any good, <hi>caremdo magis quàm fruendo.</hi> Contraries are the beſt Commentaries one upon another, and their mutuall oppoſition the beſt expoſition. The thunder of the Cannon (the language of war) is the beſt Rhetorique to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend peace: the horror of darknes, proves the benefit of light to be heavenly: health is then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred amongſt us, when it brings letters of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation from ſicknes: Anarchie is the beſt foile unto a well-temperd government, whether in Church or State. When a people have found by experience how dangerous defection is, then they wiſh for, and rejoyce in the hopes of a reſtitution.</p>
            <p n="3">3. God in wiſedome ſuffers ſuch decaies, that he may get unto himſelfe a great Name, and more glory, in exerciſing his divine power &amp; skill, for the recovering of a ruinous Nation. Preſervation is <hi>bonum optabile,</hi> but reſtitution is <hi>bonum mirabile.</hi> This it was that magnifyed Chriſts cure of the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, which had the bloody iſſue, that he healed her ſuddenly, when ſhe had ſpent all her eſtate upon the Phyſicions,<note place="margin">Mark 5.25.</note> and was never the better.</p>
            <p>Now the obſervation I ſhall raiſe from hence, is this, <hi>That Reſtitution is a great mercy to Church or Nation.</hi> I will prove it very breifly from the notion
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:29664:11"/> importance of the word. Reſtitution is cordiall, it is healing, it is joynting, it is ſetling, therefore a great bleſſing. <hi>It is Cordiall.</hi> That which is reſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative, is cordiall, and that which is cordiall, is reſtaurative. The whole heart of this Kingdome of <hi>Judah,</hi> our Prophet tels us, (at the fift verſe of this chapter,) <hi>The whole heart was faint.</hi> great need they had therefore of a Cordiall or a Reſtaurative. The greater their neceſſitie was, the more gracious is the promiſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2: <hi>Reſtitution is healing.</hi> When a man is heal'd of a Sicknes or diſtemper, then is he ſaid to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored: ſo this people were at preſent in a very Sick and diſtempered condition: <hi>The whole head ſick, from the ſole of the foot even unto the head, there was no ſoundneſſe, but wounds, and bruiſes, and putrified ſores;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>verſe</hi> 5.6.</note> 
               <hi>they had not been cloſed, neither bound up, neither mollified with oyntment.</hi> Great need they had therefore of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and reſtoring: and ſtill the greater their need, the more gracious the promiſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3: <hi>Reſtitution is joynting.</hi> 6. <hi>Gala.</hi> 1. <hi>If a man be overtaken in a fault, yee which are ſpirituall, reſtore ſuch an one in the ſpirit of meeknes:</hi> the word is (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) ſet in joynt, or ſet the bone that is broken of ſuch an one. <hi>The earth and all the inhabitants thereof are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved:</hi> (ſaith the Pſalmiſt) <hi>I beare up the Pillars of it: Diſſolved,</hi> that is, diſcompacted, diſjoynted.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm</hi> 75.2.</note>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:29664:12"/> Now when God is pleaſed to bear up a Nation thus disjoynted, it is a great mercie; but much more, when he ſhall reſtore it, and joynt it again, that it is able in ſome meaſure to ſupport in ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, <hi>Reſtitution is ſetling. Mat:</hi> 17:11. <hi>Elias ſhall firſt come and reſtore all things:</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) ſhall ſettle or eſtabliſh all things, and the word ſignifies properly, <hi>to eſtabliſh, (per collocationem in proprio loco)</hi> by reſtoring things and perſons to their proper pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Now aske a man, whoſe ſpirits were wel-nigh ſpent, how good a reſtaurative Cordiall is? aske a man, that hath been long ſick, it health be not a great mercie? aske a man, that hath broken a leg or an Arme, how good it is to have them ſafely ſet? aske one, that hath been baniſhed from his Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, his habitation, his inheritance, how com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable it is to be reſtored to them, and ſetled in the poſſeſſion of them again? ſuch a mercy is reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion unto a people, it is Cordiall, healing, joint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſetling.</p>
            <p>I will apply this in a few words. 1: For infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation. What God promiſed to Judah, he hath in a great meaſure performed to us. He hath after much fainting, diſtemper, disjoynting and diſloca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, granted us a Reſtitution. He hath reſtored us our Native and undoubted Soveraigne, our ancient Governement, both in Church and State,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:29664:12"/> our fundamentall Lawes, our Liberties, our peace, and (I hope) his own gracious favour with them all. I need not ſay much of this: a man that hath felt the fire, need not to be told that it is hot; and ſeeing the advantages which ariſe from this reſtitution unto the whole Nation, are ſo ſenſible, I need not tell you, how great a mercy it is. Perhaps there are ſome that think this reſtitution but a relapſe: I intend not to trouble my ſelfe to convince them; I pray God reſtore them alſo to their right judgements in his due time.</p>
            <p n="2">2: For excitation. One reſtitution deſerves ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Gods <hi>(Reſtituam)</hi> ſhould ſtir us up to thinke of a <hi>(quid retribuam,) what ſhall</hi> I <hi>render to the Lord for all his benefits?</hi> Gods Reſtitution was free, but ours is due, and ſo much the more due, becauſe his was free. <hi>Hezekiah</hi> is blamed for not rendring according to the benefit that he had received, and wrath was threatned to all <hi>Judah</hi> &amp; <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> for it. 2. <hi>Chro:</hi> 32.25. Let us therefore (as the Apoſtle exhorts) 13. <hi>Hebr:</hi> 15. <hi>Offer unto God the ſacrifice of praiſe continually, that is the fruit of our lipps, giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thankes to his name.</hi> Let us take heed, leſt as <hi>Philip</hi> branded his ſouldier (that beg'd the lands of one that had entertaind him kindly) with <hi>ingratus hoſpes</hi> on his fore-head; ſo God brand not us with the ignominious note of <hi>the unthankefull Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:29664:13"/>3: For Caution, in the words of our Saviour, <hi>Ioh:</hi> 5.14. <hi>Behold, thou art made whole, goe thy way and ſin no more.</hi> Sin is a forfeiture of all. Let none be offended, if I beſpeake this honourable Audience in the language of <hi>Samuel</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.24. <hi>Fear the Lord &amp; ſerve him in truth, and with all your hearts; for conſider how great things he hath done for you; but if ye ſhall ſtill do wickedly, ye ſhall be conſumed both ye and your King.</hi> So much of the firſt particular, what it is, that is promiſed, <hi>Reſtitution;</hi> I <hi>will reſtore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I come to the ſecond: a reſtitution, of whom? of Judges and Counſellours. Who are meant by Judges &amp; Counſellours, I have ſhewed you before. I ſhall chooſe now to ſpeak of them, as taken in the ſtricter ſenſe, and give you this Concluſion; <hi>That good Judges are a great bleſſing to a Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now there are ſeverall Qualifications required to the Conſtitution of a good Judge: 1. The good judge is carefull, that he act nothing but by Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from a lawfull Power: or elſe, I know not how he can anſwer that queſtion,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 2 14.</note> 
               <hi>(quis conſtituit te judicem)</hi> who made thee a judge and a Ruler? In our Nation all lawfull Authority is derivatively fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the King; the <hi>poteſtas judiciaria,</hi> the power of jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging doth primarily belong to him, it is one of his <hi>jura Regalia:</hi> a Man therefore muſt have his Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to the Office of judge from him, or elſe he is
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:29664:13"/> an intruder. <hi>Submit your ſelves to the King as ſupream, and to Governours as to them that are ſent by him.</hi> 1 <hi>Pet:</hi> 2:13: if they have not their Miſſion from him, there is no ſubmiſſion due to them.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The good judge is juſt and impartiall in the diſtribution of juſtice. When he puts on his Robes he puts off his relations to any: This is indeed one of the <hi>primae qualitates,</hi> that conſtitute a good judge to be no reſpecter of perſons, nor taker of gifts. I have read of a notable ſtory of <hi>Canuſus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cauſſin</hi> in his holy Court.</note> who having examined twelve Theeves, and condemned them, one of them pleaded, that he was extracted from roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all bloud; it is reaſon (ſaid the King) ſome grace ſhould be done to him, let him have the higheſt gib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet. And <hi>Cauſſin</hi> tels us, that in <hi>Juſtinian</hi>'s times, judges uſed to take an Oath with a ſolemn execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; an Oath to maintain Religion and juſtice ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their power; with this execration, that if they did corruptly, The horrour of Cain,<note place="margin">Gen 4 13.14. 2 King 5.27. Mat. 27.5.</note> the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſie of Gehazi, and the portion of Judas might fall upon them. You know what are the things that corrupt men in Office, thy are bribes, <hi>every one loveth gifts, and followeth after rewards,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov: 29.4.</note> is our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets complaint, concerning the corrupt Judges of Judah: and although men keep touch ſtones to try gold, yet gold certainly is a notable touch ſtone,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Fuller.</note> whereby to try men. But now as the honeſt Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:29664:14"/> preſerves her chaſtity, ſo doth the good Judge preſerve his integrity, and that is, by giving no encouragement unto any to corrupt him. <hi>He deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the gain of oppreſſion, and ſhaketh his hands from holding of bribes. Iſa.</hi> 33:15: He will take no bribes himſelfe, and he deteſts that hypocriſie of the Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicant Friers, who will touch no money themſelves, but have a Boy with a bagge to receive it for them.</p>
            <p n="3">3: We will conceive the good Judge (when in the execution of his office) diveſted of paſſion, and his mind ſo clear, that there is nothing to diſturbe his judgement: and having this command of his affections, he can hear a ſimple witneſſe ſpeak im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinencies, without impatience; which if duely conſidered, doth argue a great (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) or ſtrength of mind: the good Judge hath ſo much judgement, as to conſider the Ruſticity and homelineſſe of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people in giving of evidence, that they muſt be impertinent, before they can be pertinent. But however he exerciſe thus much patience towards a ſimple Witneſſe, yet he hath ſo much prudence, as not to bear it in a profeſſed Pleader: he will not ſuffer a Lawyer, with multitude of words &amp; queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, in a plaine caſe, to darken the cauſe, conſound the Jurie, or puzzle the Witneſſes.</p>
            <p n="4">4: The good Judge is Couragious. What need he to fear? when he hath God, and the King,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:29664:14"/> and the Lawes, and the teſtimony of a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to bear him out, if he do uprightly. It is ſaid of <hi>Cato</hi> and <hi>Fabricius,</hi> that the Sun might ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er be ſtayed or altered in his Race, than they in the courſe of Juſtice; it requires a ſtout ſpirit, to be thus ſteddie. He had need to be a man of ſpirit, that muſt neglect the diſpleaſure and frownes; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject the Letters and Suits of great men; as Judges muſt doe, if they would be as <hi>Cato</hi> and <hi>Fabricius.</hi> Had not he need to be a man of courage, that muſt (as it often falls out with Judges) maintain right againſt might? had not he need to be of an undaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſpirit, that muſt turne the wheel over the wicked, withſtand the inundation of prophaneſs, and ſuppreſſe the Roaring Ladds, that fear neither God, nor man? what was it that made <hi>Pilate</hi> yeild to the condemnation of Chriſt, but his fear?<note place="margin">John 19.12</note> 
               <hi>if thou let this man goe</hi> (ſay they) <hi>thou art not Coeſars freind:</hi> whereas a <hi>Coeſar</hi> indeed (ſuch an one as our <hi>Coeſar</hi>) accounts it an abomination, either to condemne the Innocent, or to Juſtifie the wicked for a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
            <p n="5">5: The good judge is not delatory. He makes not a Trojan Seige of a ſuite, but doth what he can to bring it to a ſpeedie iſſue. He thinkes it enough for one partie to loſe the cauſe, and therefore endeavours, what he can, to leſſen the charges.
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:29664:15"/> 
               <hi>Lewis</hi> the 12th uſed to ſay, delatory Juſticiaries ſtretched the leather with their teeth.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cauſſin</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the practice of juſtice.</note> I have read a notable ſtory taken (as my Authour ſaith) out of the Chronicles of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> concerning one <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doricke</hi> King of the Romans. <hi>Juvenalis</hi> a widow (having a ſuit depending in the Court three years, which might have been diſpatched in a few dayes) makes her complaint to the King: he demanded who were her Judges, and ſent to them to expedite her Cauſe, which they did in two dayes. After they had done, <hi>Theodoricke</hi> ſends for them again (as they thought, to applaud them for their expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition) being come, he asked them what was the reaſon, they defer'd that for three years, which they could diſpatch in two dayes? they made no Apologie (that I read of) for their deferring, for it is likely they had none to make: but they ſaid, they had made ſuch ſpeedy diſpatch upon his ſpeciall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commendation. How (ſaid the King) when I put you into Office, did I not conſigne all Pleas and proceedings to you, and particularly thoſe of wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows? you deſerve death, for ſpinning out a bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe three years, which might be drawne to a period in two dayes: and ſo commanded both their heads to be ſmitten off.</p>
            <p>I cannot ſtand to adde colours to every lineament of a good judge. Let it ſuffice, that I only point
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:29664:15"/> at the reſt. 6: The good Judge is a ſpecial Patron of Widowes and Orphans; and therefore takes ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall cognizance of their actions, for fear there ſhould be any corruption in their Advocates. This is God's high Style, <hi>pſalme</hi> 68:5: <hi>A Father of the fatherleſs, and a judge of the Widow is God in his holy habitation.</hi> For this it was that God was ſo much incenſed againſt the judges of Judah <hi>They judge not the fatherleſſe, neither doth the Cauſe of the Widow come before them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7: Mercy is a neceſſary qualification of a good Judge. They ſay a Butcher may not be of the jury for Life &amp; Death, much leſſe ſhould ſuch an one ſit as judge. The good judge therefore (ſo far as he may with ſafety to his Conſcience) remits of the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour of the Law, eſpecially where indulgence may work amendment. He inſults not over Malefac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, with opprobrious and taunting language, be their crimes never ſo foule: but takes occaſion from thence to pity the depraved nature of man, which is ſubject to ſuch Exorbitances. He pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounces not the ſentence of condemnation without great commiſeration; and is careful, that they (who are not worthy to live) may by the inſtruction of ſome able Miniſter, be the better fitted to dye, that however the fleſh be deſtroyed, the ſpirit may be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the day of the Lord Jeſus.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 5.5.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8: The good judge is not <hi>Gallio</hi>-like,<note place="margin">Acts 18.14.</note> careleſſe
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:29664:16"/> in things that do concern Religion. He conſiders that his Majeſtie is <hi>Cuſtos utriuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> tabulae,</hi> and hath by Deputation made him ſo too.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, The good judge is a good Man; One that feareth God, and eſcheweth evill; of ſuch up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſſe &amp; integrity, that his Converſation is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary to all inferiour Magiſtrates. One that keeps a judicature within his own breaſt, and daily tryes all his actions in the Court of Conſcience. One that makes conſciene of his duty towards God, as well as the King, remembring that account he hath to give, ere long, to the judge of all the earth. One that is devout in his Cloſet, ſtrict in his Family, and thinks himſelfe as honourable, with his Train wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on him to the Church, as to the Court. In a word one ſo pious, juſt, charitable, temperate, and free from vice, that he doth as much good by his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample as by his Authority Thus I have ſhown you who is a good judge: and let none think, that I have extracted this out of Sir <hi>Thomas Moore</hi>'s <hi>Utopia,</hi> and given you the deſcription of a man, that never was nor ever will be; you may take <hi>Iob</hi> for a proof &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident of all that I have ſaid, <hi>Iob</hi> 29:11:</p>
            <p>Now that judges, that are thus good, muſt needs be a great bleſſing to a Nation, is not very neceſſary to be proved. I know, you have in your owne thoughts prevented me, that I need ſay nothing
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:29664:16"/> Both the time and the matter do now require, that I ſhould direct my ſpeech unto you (my Lords &amp; Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen) for whoſe honour as well as inſtruction this Exerciſe is obſerved: I beſeech you therefore, as <hi>Paul</hi> once did <hi>Agrippa, Acts</hi> 26:3: <hi>that you would hear me patiently.</hi> I confeſs, I am every way one of the leaſt of the Sons of my Mother, and ſhould ſcarce have ſeen your Lordſhips for the Crowd, had I not been ſet up in this Sycamore Tree: but now I have the honour not only to be your Spectatour, but your Monitour.</p>
            <p>I will only premiſe two things to that, which I have to ſay. The firſt is this, that I ſpeak any thing in this kind, is more becauſe it is become cuſtomary, than becauſe I think it neceſſary. The ſecond is, that determination of the School-Men, who ſay, that an Angel of an inferiour Order may inflame, but can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not illuminate an Angell of a ſuperiour Order: this is the utmoſt, that I aime at, to erect your Zeal, I preſume not to add to your knowledge. This be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing premiſed, I ſhall diſpatch what I have to ſay, in three Words.</p>
            <p n="1">1 My Lords and Gentlemen, you know what a ſtrict Proclamation his Majeſty (out of his Princely piety, not policy) hath ſet out, againſt Vicious, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauched, and Prophane Perſons: and yet iniquity ſeems to abound; this calls aloud for your obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:29664:17"/> and regulation. As I would not have them who have been accounted the King's foes, to ſleight his promiſes; ſo nor thoſe, that are deſirous to be reputed his friends, to neglect his precepts. Piety and Loyalty are as conſiſtent, as God and the King; Curſed be he that goes about to ſet them at variance. I acknowledge indeed, that you ſee moſt what with other mens eyes, and cannot puniſh abuſes (unleſſe you ſee them) without complaint and information from others: yet verily, the prophaneneſſe of ſome men is ſuch, that they declare their ſin as <hi>Sodom,</hi> they hide it not;<note place="margin">Iſa. 3.9.</note> and what men do not ſeek to hide, you may ſee if you will. To paſſe by drunkenneſſe, ſwearing and ſuch like, how common is the propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the Lords-Day: however God may ſeem to winke at it, yet he takes notice of it, and will not ſuffer it, that we ſhould ſo far entrench upon his Royaltie, as to make his Day either a day of buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,<note place="margin">ſee <hi>Trap:</hi> on John 21 1.</note> or a day of pleaſure. Very ſtrict were they in the obſervation of this day, in the primitive times: for when the queſtion was put <hi>(annon obſervâſti diem dominicum)</hi> haſt thou obſerved the Lords day?<note place="margin">vid. <hi>Ignat.</hi> Epiſt 3. ad <hi>Magn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ:</hi>
               </note> the anſwer was returned, <hi>(Chriſtianus ſum intermittere non poſſum)</hi> I am a Chriſtian I may not do otherwiſe. But now nothing more ordinary, than for thoſe that call themſelves Chriſtians, to neglect the obſervation of it. It concerns you that are in Authority, both by
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:29664:17"/> your examples and injunctions, to ſuppreſſe this inundation of impiety; or elſe it will endanger to bring upon the Nation great wrath. It is true, God hath mercifully, and miraculouſly reſtored us, but remember what <hi>Ezra</hi> once ſaid, <hi>Ezra</hi> 9.13. <hi>After thou haſt given us ſuch deliverance as this, ſhould we again break thy Commandements, wouldſt thou not be angry with us, till thou hadſt conſumed us, ſo that there ſhould be no remnant nor eſcaping?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2: My Lords &amp; Gentlemen, you know, what ſtrict Laws we have againſt <hi>Recuſants,</hi> which the wiſedome of his Majeſties Royall Predeceſſors, and Progenitors, with their Counſels, thought fit to Enact againſt them; looking on them only as Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, becauſe Natives, but otherwiſe accounting them the moſt dangerous enemies both to Church and State. And yet it is reported, that ſome of them are ſoe confident, as to promiſe unto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a toleration; which they could not doe, if thoſe Lawes were put in execution. My Lords, you know, that ſuch a toleration is contrary to the Lawes of the Land: and the reverend Biſhops will ſoon ſatisfie you, that it is contrary to the Lawes of God and this Church. If any of them have done ſervice to his Majeſty, or thoſe that were in exile with him, they are ſure to be well rewarded; who wiſheth that they may not? but we pay them too
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:29664:18"/> deare for their Courteſies, if we lay them our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion in pawne for them; and if their Religion be tolerated, it is to be feared leſt in time it may juſtle out ours. I have read of a prophecy indeed, <hi>That Anti-chriſt ſhould never overcome</hi> Venice, <hi>nor</hi> Paris, <hi>nor</hi> London; I ſay <hi>Amen</hi> to it: yet I ſhould much fear the laſt, if <hi>Recuſancy</hi> ſhould have a Toleration.</p>
            <p n="3">3: My Lords, you know, what an enemy <hi>Schiſme</hi> hath been to the welfare of this Church &amp; Nation, and is ſtill like to be. It concernes your Honours, as you are Counſellours, to give your advice in this doubtfull and difficult matter. Some, it may be, are of opinion, that as the times produced this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temper, ſo time muſt cure it againe. I do not ſay, but this remedie may prove effectuall, but I cannot ſay, that it will: the hazard we run by ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction is certain, but what the iſſue of it may be, is uncertain. I do not conceive, that the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of this ſubject, is out of your Lord-ſhips Cognizance: for it is true, if theſe contentions about Church-matters were only agitated in the Schooles and had no influence upon the State, the matter were leſſe, but we ſee frequently, that Tumults and diſtractions in the State, ariſe from hence.</p>
            <p>It is a good way to remove ſchiſme, to conſider firſt what indeed Schiſme is: that is the very ſubject of the queſtion, and if we erre in this we doe ſtumble
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:29664:18"/> 
               <hi>in limine.</hi> Schiſme ſeems to me to be, <hi>a groundleſſe rending of the Churches Communion, joyned with a contempt of the Churches Authoritie.</hi> And therefore I ſuppoſe, though a man be in ſome things diſſatisfied (ſo he give but all due reſpect and reverence to Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall authority) he may be ſaid to be ſcrupulous or at the moſt erronious, but not Schiſmaticall. All I will ſay more is this, the diſeaſe is intricate, it may be ſuperficially, but it will never be ſoundly healed, till a narrow ſearch be made into the nature of it. Thus I have made bold to point out to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipps, the three great Troublers of our <hi>Iſrael, Prophaneneſſe, Poperie,</hi> and <hi>Schiſme;</hi> which ſo far as they fall upon the ſtate, require the obſervation and inſpection of you, who are by your Office, <hi>Phyſicians and Miniſters of State.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Lords: I have no more to adde, but to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulate this Honourable Aſſembly, and to pray that the Lord of Lords would be a ſheild to protect you, a Sunne to guide you, an exceeding great Reward to honour, comfort and bleſſe you, in all your Counſells, Judgements, Journeys, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnes. Unto this God, who is one Eſſence, and three Perſons, the King immortall, inviſible, the only wiſe God, be honour and Glory, for ever and ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
